Guide to the Ireland House Oral History Collection AIA.030
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
Ireland House Oral History Collection
2005-2010
AIA.030
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
3.25 linear feet (4 boxes)
Multi-generational interviews conducted since 2005 as part of an undergraduate oral history course for the Irish Studies program at New York University, under the auspices of Glucksman Ireland House and also by doctoral students and faculty.
Glucksman Ireland House. New York University.
Provenance
Interviews were conducted by students in the Irish Studies program. Materials are transferred to the Archives after access copies of interviews have been created on DVDs and transcripts typed up. Interviews continue to arrive in the Archives annually.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Irish Immigration Reform Movement Records AIA 016
Access Restrictions
Open for research with restrictions as noted per individual interview.
Arrangement
Arranged into one alphabetical series by interviewee. Dates recorded refer to date of interview.
Historical/Biographical Note
Multi-generational interviews conducted since 2005 as part of an undergraduate oral history course for the Irish Studies program at New York University, under the auspices of Glucksman Ireland House.
Scope and Contents note
The Ireland House Oral History Collection consists of multi-generational interviews conducted since 2005 as part of an undergraduate oral history course for the Irish Studies program at New York University, under the auspices of Glucksman Ireland House. Each interview has been transferred to DVD; some interviews are on multiple DVDs. The collection includes summaries of interviews (not transcripts) and supporting biographical and background information on the interviewee. Original tapes of the interviews are housed separately.
Benson, Sean; Burns, Edward, 1968-; King, Peter T., 1944-; Minihane, Sean; Sexton, John; Irish Americans; Irish Americans |x Social life and customs.; Oral histories (document genres); Transcripts.
- B
  - Beirne, Hilary, Oct 29, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Benson, Sean (b. 1960), one of the organizers of the Irish Immigration Reform Movement, former Executive Director of the Emerald Isle Immigration Center and a member of its board., Nov 29, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
  - Boucher, Jack, Jan 23, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Boylan, Jim, Feb 26, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Burns, Edward Sr. (former policeman), Nov 14, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Burns, Edward Jr. (b. 1968), is a writer, director, and actor who shot to fame in 1995 when his film, The Brothers McMullen, which he wrote, directed, and starred in, about three Irish American brothers coming of age on Long Island., Oct 30, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- C
  - Cagney, Bridget (b. 1937) retired program analyst for the Institute of International Education and a member of "Point Thank You,” a post-9/11 support group in New York City., Nov 8, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Campbell, Colm (b. 1935), Executive Director of the New York Irish Center in Long Island City, former Director of the Irish Apostolate USA, and former Director of Youth Services for the Diocese of Down and Connor in Northern Ireland., Nov 13, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Carey, Governor Hugh, Jun 25, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Carroll, Martina, Feb 20, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Carroll, Patrick, Apr 7, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Casey, Sr. Noreen, Apr 16, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Cassidy, Daniel, Jun 20, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Clancy, Cummin, Apr 29, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Clancy, Liam, Mar 29, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Conlon, Ray, Aug 24, 2010 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Connolly, Marie, Jun 23, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Cook, Terri Connolly, Oct 30, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Costello, Frank, Apr 9, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Crotty, Paul, Mar 10, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Culhane, Noreen M. (b. 1950), an Executive Vice President at the New York Stock Exchange and the 1970 New York Rose of Tralee, Dec 7, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Cullen, Fr. Daniel, May 6, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Curran, Sean, Mar 28, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- D
  - D'Arcy, Kathleen Walsh (two interviews, Feb 12 and Apr 22), 2009 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Dennehy, Thomas, Mar 19, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Dolan, Joan (b. 1937), former McNiff dancer, founding member of the Bedford (NY) Ceili group, and wife of Irish traditional pianist Felix Dolan., Nov 16, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Donnelly, John, Oct. 25, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Driscoll, John, Apr 21, 2010 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Dunne, Vincent (b. 1935), a forty-two year veteran of the New York Fire Department who writes and lectures nationally on fire and firefighter safety., Nov 13, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- F
  - Fallon, John J. (b. 1919) retired Principal of Bay Ridge High School and former president of the American Irish Teachers Association, Nov 16, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Fanning, Charles, Nov 4, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Feighery, John, May 1, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Flanagan, James, Feb 17, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Flannelly, Adrian (2 inteviews Nov 13 and Nov 19), 2008 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Fleming, Tom, Feb 27, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - French, Mary, Feb 2, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- G
  - Goldman, Ira, Nov 11, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Gormley, Sean, Oct 28, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Grange, Fr. Sean, Oct 29, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Greene, John, Mar 27, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Grimes, Claire (two interviews Feb 4 and Feb 11; publisher Irish Echo), 2009 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Grimes, Patrick Jr., Dec 5, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 43)
- H
  - Hamill, Peter (author, journalist), Oct 22, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Hartigan, Daniel (two interviews, Mar 29 and Dec 9), 2008 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Hayes, Catriona, Mar 9, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Hayes, Eddie, Mar 9, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Hayes, Thomas, Jun 2, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Hurley, Patrick (IIRM), Oct 31, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- J
  - Johnston, Lisa, Mar 26, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- K
  - Kelly, Donald A. (b. 1935), retired Senior Vice President of Emigrant Savings Bank and President of the Executive Committee of the Emerald Isle Immigration Center, Nov 15, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Kelly, Patrick, M.D., Jan 17, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Kelly, Sr. Theresa (b. 1934), a member of the Sisters of Mercy of the Mid-Atlantic Community who, after a long teaching career, retired as Principal of Our Lady of Refuge in East Flatbush, Brooklyn (NY)., Nov 8, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Kelly, Thomas, Dec 14, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - King, Peter T. (b. 1944), Republican Congressman from Long Island and one of the architects of the Northern Ireland peace process in the 1990s., Nov 28, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- L
  - Lavery, Bobby, Jun 3, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Laverty, Charles (two interviews Oct 16, 2009 and Feb 19, 2010), 2009-2010 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- M
  - Maguire, Anne, Jan 24, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Mahon, Pat (b. 1958), an executive with Bear Stearns and Co., and a 1973 All-Ireland button accordian champion., Nov 14, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - McAllister, Brian (b. 1932), president of McAllister Towing & Transport, a tugboat firm operating on the Eastern seaboard but principally in New York harbor., Nov 7, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - McCarthy, Sr. Rita, Apr 8, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - McFadden, Stephen, May 19, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - McGimpsey, William, Jul 24, 2010 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - McKeown, Susan (musician), Nov 3, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - McManus, Jim, Mar 5, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - McMullan, Mary, Oct 28, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Minihane, Sean (IIRM), Oct 25, 2007; (no transcript or summary) (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Miskell, Frank, Mar 21, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Motherway, Patrick, Jun 8, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Mulvihill, James, Nov 7, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Murphy, Sr. Bernice, Apr 8, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Murphy, James (Jim), Feb 6, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Murphy, James (Jim), Oct 19, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Murphy, Mary, Nov 14, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Murphy, Maureen, Oct 23, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Murphy, Sr. Regina (b. 1939), the property manager for the Sisters of Charity of New York and an advocate for corporate responsibility, fought hard to establish the McBride Principles., Nov 9, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- O
  - O'Callaghan, Patricia, Nov 2, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - O'Driscoll, Mae (b. 1939) retired Assistant Vice President of the facilities management department for J.P. Morgan Chase, one of the organizers of the Irish Immigration Reform Movement, and a Trustee and Secretary of the Executive Committee of the Emerald Isle Immigration Center., Nov 18, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - O'Hara, Mary, Oct 8, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - O'Rourke, Hugh, Jan 14, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - O'Rourke, Mary, Apr 17, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - O'Rourke, Sheila, Jun 1, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - O'Sullivan, Sheena, Feb 13, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 35)
- P
  - Prendiville, Sean, May 31, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 36)
- Q
  - Quigley, Martin, May 21, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Quinn, Charles B., Jun 10, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Quinn, Peter, Nov 11, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Quinn, Sean, Feb 7, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 40)
- R
  - Reidy, Sr. Virgilius, Apr 8, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Rogers, James, Oct 9. 2009 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Rooney, James E. (b. 1967) director of Firstlink at the Univeristy of Pittsburgh's Institute for Entrepreneurial Excellence, Katz Graduate School of Business, and grandson of Pittsburgh Steelers founder Art Rooney., Nov 9, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Ryan, Fr. Gerald R. (b. 1920), pastor of St. Luke’s R.C. Church in the South Bronx and the longest serving pastor in the Archdiocese of New York., Nov 17, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Rygor, Stanley and Kathleen, May 14, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 45)
- S
  - Sax, Eithne Golden (b. 1919) retired multilingual translort for the United Nations, daughter of Irish nationalist organizer Peter Golden, and pupil of Irish republican author Ernie O’Malley., Nov 2, 2006 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Scally, Robert J. (b. 1937), retired Professor of History, New York University and inaugural Director, Glucksman Ireland House, New York University., Nov 20, 2006 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Sexton, John E. (b. 1942), President of New York University and former Dean of its School of Law., Dec 2, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Shanley, John Patrick, Nov 5, 2008 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Shea, Sr. Catherine, Jun 12, 2009 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Smyth, Tommy (sports announcer), Oct 24, 2008 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Smyth, Treasa Goodwin (radio personality; wife of Tommy Smyth), Nov 6, 2009 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- T
  - Tatty, Matthew, Mar 7, 2009 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Tanner, Peggy, Nov 24, 2008 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Taylor, Joe, Jan 29, 2009 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- W
  - Waters, Sr. Victor, Apr 8, 2009 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Z
  - Zurell, Eileen, Nov 6, 2008 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Duplicate CDs (Box 3)
- Original recordings: for Staff use only (Box 4)